hi this is part 2 of the video tutorial
series
what is the magellan course in this
tutorial we are going to look at
dialectical reasoning through the work
of gebser in his notion of the
structures of consciousness in our last
tutorial we talked about the magellan
course be being interested in crossing a
frontier and that frontier was between
the current state where our reasoning is
dialectical has a dialectical dynamic
into a potential situation which is not
dialectical but represents a new way of
thinking that is not dialectical and so
I think it is important to understand
the evolution of dialectical reasoning
reasoning how it came to be what exactly
characterizes in accounts for
dialectical reasoning before we go on to
investigate the possibility of new types
of consciousness and new structures of
reasoning that do not operate
dialectically so we're going to look at
this today in terms of gaps or
structures of consciousness and gap sirs
work the ever-present origin and in the
subsequent videos part three we'll look
at dialectical reasoning through
developmental theory and in part four
we'll look at dialectical reasoning
through the history of philosophy but
for today we are going to look at
dialectical reasoning through gap sirs
work from the ever-present
origin his book the present origin and
this notion of the evolution of the
structures of consciousness
so I hope you enjoy this tutorial gebser
saw the evolution of human consciousness
as proceeding through great epochal
shifts and he uses that term epic so if
we imagine three waves or three great
epochal shifts shifts ethics of
consciousness and the way he saw these
epochs arising were through phases so
each epoch would have a phase in the
phases would go from latent or the early
days to efficient phase the height of
the maturity of the essence of the
structure consciousness to a deficient
phase so we can think of this epoch here
between these two points as the epoch we
are in this epoch here as the epoch that
came before and so this you know just
before we start moving into our epoch
our structure of consciousness today we
would have come from the deficient stage
of the previous epoch and moving out of
our structure of consciousness
developing toward the new we move we'll
see we moving into a new latent stage of
the new structure of consciousness now
each of these structures of
consciousness can be identified by the
types of reasoning that are evident
through works of art
through philosophy through language
through different cultural traditions
and structures and so what we're going
to look at today is the current
structure of consciousness over the last
2,000 years is called the mental
structure the previous structure of
consciousness gifts are called the
mythic structure not to be confused with
the mythic level of development within
the mental structure and the upcoming or
the new structure of consciousness gaps
are called integral again not to be
confused with the term integral in terms
of developmental theory within the
mental structure and we will look at
developmental theory within the mental
structure in the next video so each of
these epics each of structures of
consciousness have a three phase kind of
evolutionary momentum within the mental
structure of consciousness that we are
in now the latent form of reasoning gaps
are called ocn ik the efficient form of
reasoning gaps are called pyramidal and
we'll see why and the deficient form a
reason
gaps are called perspectival and in
general gifts are left these the detail
of the integral structure blank and so
this is the territory where we're we're
doing hypothetical work we're trying to
fill in the blanks in this territory in
the magellan course but be consistent
with some of the processes
gebser described now another thing in
terms of what we're looking at are these
three types of reasoning build up to
what we understand as dialectical
reasoning so the movement from the
oceanic to the pyramidal to the
perspectival is a development of
dialectical reasoning from the history
prior to this phase the mythic was was
not yet dialectical and in fact even
oceanic reasoning is not yet dialectical
and so our hypothesis and this would be
consistent with gebser is that beyond
the epoch of the mental structure of
consciousness the types of reasoning
would be no longer dialectical so that's
the hypothesis that we go from the
not-yet dialectical epoch through this
process of the development of
dialectical reasoning within this
evolutionary epic to a shift and
evolutionary shift to a new structure
consciousness the integral consciousness
drip structure of consciousness where it
is no longer dialectical and that would
be the reasoning behind the magellan
course trying to look into this
hypothetical territory to give it more
detail the way gebser
has detailed the reasoning structures as
they develop through the mental epoch
okay so that's basically the grand over
view so what we can do is parse out and
look at OC anak thinking for oceanic
reasoning oceanic reasoning was not
quite yet
dialectical and it proceeds from the
mythic and gaps are dismayed these
distinguished distinctions the mythic
he's called the mythic he called
two-dimensional and the characteristic
of a mythical this would be the mythic
stepping back here the characteristic of
the mythical is that there was always a
return never a progression never never a
progression and so we see this in mythic
cultures today our mythical systems so
you have cycles seasonal cycles where
they're spraying their summer or there's
fall there's winter in their spring so
there's always a return a mandala like
mentality there's a the temperance or
the time frame is always cyclical or
periodic Zeus flew around the heavens in
a diurnal pattern there's tales of birth
death and rebirth in cyclical patterns
like the pale of the Phoenix
so the mythic had this two-dimensional
character to it
in the problem with the mythic is that
it represented in its deficient stage
just before the new epoch the problem
with the mythic is that it became you
know it was completely closed but all
the systems had been completely closed
within this endless cycle of return so
the cultural structures the cultural
systems the power structures the kinds
of justifications human humans used for
moral and ethic jurisprudence they all
ended up having no ability to get beyond
this closure this is the way things are
they will always be the same there's no
there's no the illusion that things
change is defeated by the fact that
things always return so caps are talked
about this this this problem with
closure of the system that created the
impetus or the dynamics for the mythic
type of reasoning this two dimensional
reasoning to move into a new type of
reasoning in the first indication of
that gebser calls oceanic reasoning
so if we look at Oceana Creason again
just to back up mythic wheezing had this
polar structure so if this was the
beginning you reason you reason you come
back
there's always a return and that
represented closure and the mythic style
of reasoning it's two dimensional so you
have two dimensional with the closure
and the gaps are called this polar
reasoning in this closure represented an
evolutionary synth dynamics to move
toward new types of reasoning so we get
to oceanic reasoning which gaps are
called oceanic because it has wave-like
movements that have indications of
progression but that eventually our
recursive also return the way the polar
reasoning does but in this gap Xerces
the beginning of a movement away from
polar reasoning and so for example in
oceanic reasoning he uses a quote from
Heraclitus and the quote goes souls
death becomes water water becomes
so there's a sense that there's a
progression from one term to the next
and then a progression to another term
this is the wave-like structure of
oceanic but then the way this quote ends
is from Earth
water from water soul and so you see
despite this progression there's a real
ooping back to origin and so there is
this is oceanic thinking is the latent
precursor of dialectical thinking for
the efficient phase of the mental
structure of consciousness and so we go
from mythic which has got this closed
two dimensional but closed reasoning
cycle to oceanic with gives which gives
us some indication of this progression
to other terms relating the beginning
term to other terms but with the
completion of the thought argument
always going still going back to close
on the origin still have this mentality
like quality so that's why it calls
oceanic thinking latent it's it shows
signs of moving from polar reasoning in
the mythic structure but it's not quite
yeah as mature of dialectical process as
the next phase that get gaps are
identifies in the mental structure the
development of the mental structure of
consciousness into the efficient phase
he calls that thinking pyramidal so we
go from the polar reasoning of a mythic
structure to the transitional phase
oceanic in its wave-like structure to
the efficient phase the pyramidal which
today we recognize as dialectical
thinking and
certainly gebser did also so now we'll
turn to the efficient phase of the
mental structure and that's pyramidal
thinking okay so we are going from the
mythic to oceanic which is the first
indication of dialectical thinking -
pyramidal thinking caps are called the
mythic two-dimensional with its closure
and he called pyramidal
three-dimensional in the reason why is
that pyramidal thinking we won't be
surprised looks like this can be
illustrated like this you have a you
have not a and then you have a
progression to a higher synthesis so
here's the origin airy term it is
contrasted with its opposite so at the
far end so if this is summer this would
be winter and instead of having a
completion in this argument Baptist to
summer this tension this gap is held
open in lieu of the search for a higher
synthesis in this higher that synthesis
gaps are talked about as the third term
for the tercio in this pyramidal or
triangular structure is what gives this
type of reasoning the label pyramidal
so now the interesting thing is that
pyramidal thinking in the term dialectic
comes from Plato and he uses the term
diuresis and what diuresis means is
separation and it refers to the ability
for the mind to hold this gap this
tension in this gap between antinomies
or opposites in order to force a higher
synthesis in order to gain a higher
synthesis and so you see some of this in
Plato and Socrates the way Socrates
would tease out the paradoxes and force
people to move to a higher level of
thinking and this paved the way for all
kinds of evolutionary advances in human
history but this notion of being of
diuresis of being able to hold these
antennae means as opposites at the end
of a spectrum was a significant
difference than what the mythic mind
could do the mythic mind would always
see these categories as turning over on
themselves in the MacDonald like fashion
and just recapitulating themselves
what we then see in terms of what
dialectical reasoning amounts to after
2,000 years of dialectical reasoning is
that you have this pyramidal thought
that leads to a higher synthesis which
then finds its antithesis that this
leads to a higher level synthesis and
after 2,000 years the whole system has
created this very progressive or
progression this notion of reasoning as
progress progress or progression and
guess who was very careful and very
pains taken to note that this concept of
progress or progression is a product of
a dialectical style of reasoning of the
mental structure of consciousness and so
when he talks about the evolution of the
structures of consciousness he does not
mean to imply or to incorporate this
mental structure of progression onto the
notion of evolution this is very
important way important point in reading
gebser that our tendency to see
evolutionary processes as progressive is
merely a condition of the mental
structure of consciousness and so this
is another kind of view that is
conditional to
and depended upon the mental structure
ethic of consciousness and so forget sir
because he was moving beyond that
conditioned mindset
he saw evolutionary change as just that
epochal shift but not necessarily
progressive and that the notion of
progression is imputed epochal shift by
the mental structure of consciousness
because of the dialectical style of
reasoning which over 2,000 years sees
this constant progression in the in
analogous to the way the mythic
structure of consciousness saw
everything as complete iteration in
return the mental structure of
consciousness sees everything as
increasingly progressing and so we hear
of the concept of complexification
complexification that systems and
evolution complexified over time and
this is merely a view of the mental
structure in its type of reasoning which
it is gives us this progressive
understanding of epochal shift so Gibson
really worked hard at making these kinds
of distinctions so people could
understand that the way we view
evolution is a byproduct of the epoch
that we are in so without a doubt there
is this the pockle shift but it it only
appears as a progressive
complexification a continual progression
in complexification because of the
dynamics the dialectical dynamics of a
mental structure
and so this pyramidal type of thinking
with it's positive consequences results
in some of its own limitations
represents the efficient phase of the
mental structure of consciousness and
the really the epical opinion for the
last two thousand years now the
questions we are in the pyramidal or
efficient stage phase of the mental
structure and we even gaps or could see
that this had already begun to become
deficient or we could say it had it
started to exhaust its useful
evolutionary usefulness as it moved into
what he called the deficient stage and
he associates that with his term for
that is perspectival and this is very
interesting because if you're familiar
with integral theory or aqua theory then
the whole notion of perspective ilysm
and Multan integral methodological
pluralism and multi-perspective ilysm is
touted as the pinnacle of rational
development in but for the very same
reasons that gebser saw what
perspectival reasoning was he sees that
he codifies this as the deficient stage
of the mental structure so there's
actually a complete
disconnect between aqua theory and GAAP
sirs notion of the perspectival phase
gap sir saw the perspectival phase of
reasoning in the mental structure as
being deficient so this is a not a small
point if you are a scholar of integral
theory it's aqua aqua version of
integral theory so why did gaps or sea
perspective ilysm as being deficient
well it's quite you know gap stirred
himself is quite complicated to read but
what I can summarize for you is that
after 2000 years of this progressive
movement to find the third term there
are three major reasons why the pinnacle
of this which is prospective ilysm is
become deficient and number one is is
that the perspectival ism is developed
because of 2,000 years of meta
theoretical division so you have higher
in high the third term represents higher
and higher levels of integration but the
situation is so complexified in so
driven by this notion of progress in
higher higher levels
that the that the there are no so there
they're no longer and any solutions okay
the solutions the enquiries become more
and more abstract more and more meta
theoretical more and more complexified
they can't solve any it doesn't solve
any more problems so in a sense it
represents a closure so there the meta
frames that are required these are not
get search terms itself represents the
kind of closure because you're
constantly moving to more and more
complex higher abstract versions of the
inquiry and so that's why he called this
phase deficient the second reason is
because the meta frames these are not
his terms this is a synopsis they exit
their own domain the domain of inquiry
so for example in Hargens and
Zimmerman's book integral ecology they
it's a compendium of hundreds of
different approaches to ecology parsed
out based upon altitude this notion of
altitude worldview the who the what the
where that it makes all these
perspective distinctions but when you
read the book interval ecology it does
not do ecology okay it does meta theory
and so the problem with perspective
ilysm is that it it creates its own map
territory confusion the map becomes so
complex and you
so compute concern with the map in its
ever increasing complexity that you
really kind of lost touch with being and
this is really the critique that gaps
are has with perspectival ISM and that
is that all these progressive ships in
the pyramidal structure of reasoning
after two thousand years has created a
transit idea of transcendence as truth
and has completely lost touch is made a
gap this gap that's being held between
has been iterated over and over and over
again so now like there's this complete
gap between this transcendent
abstraction and what he would call being
or origin in that perspective ilysm and
meta theory can no longer get at
imminence and the basic fundamental
ground of being so this is really the
biggest critique about perspective ilysm
that it starts to be distracted by its
own abstractions and it no longer what
gaps earth Kant uses the coins the term
no longer a where's the truth in being
and so what was once in the pyramidal
form efficient and evolutionarily
advantageous has become in the
perspectival form deficient in the only
place I see this an aqua theory is when
Wilbur says that aqua is a map of the
prison and this really would resonate
with gebser that perspectival ISM is a
great map but it's a map of the prison
and the prison
been generated by dialectical mind the
prison is nothing but the rarefied
abstractions of dialectical mind and so
this represents what gaps we call the
deficient phase of the mental structure
of consciousness which is this hyper
complexified dialectical reasoning so
we've moved from the mythic and it's
polar reasoning which is not yet
dialectic to the mental structure of
consciousness in its three phases the
latent phase and the latent phase which
is oceanic reasoning the efficient phase
which is pyramidal and the deficient
phase which is perspectival and so now
we want to look at what is the latent
phase of the new structure
one of the types of reasoning that gets
her seized as a candidate we just call
it a candidate for this latent phase of
the new structure he called paradoxical
reasoning and paradoxical reasoning has
this can be described as being able to
hold this gap of a and not eight let's
say so can still hold this gap so in
that sense it retains some of the
experience of diuresis or separation but
what it does is it resists the synthetic
synthetic move move or the tree resists
the synthetic or the transcendent or
abstraction the higher abstraction move
and that's why it calls it paradoxical
because it kind of rests in this
paradoxical territory just as that
without the synthetic move and what gaps
are saw it I think it's consistent with
what we see today the reason why this
alternative comes up is because the the
people that are starting to in the
history of what Gibson was looking at
starting to reason in a more paradoxical
style or all people related to either
spirituality so for example the Buddhist
scholastics
or that have some kind of reinvent with
being as a as for example Heidegger or
are interested in theology or religion
and so you have the beginning of the
Western process philosophers and so this
commonality between them is that they
were looking outside the mind or beyond
the mind to ground truth in being and in
that being in that experience of being
they found the ability to hold the mind
stable in this paradoxical state and so
paradoxical reasoning is a transitional
phase that gets our saw associated with
a movement that was not toward the
deficient phase of the mental structure
but he saw it as a transitional face he
doesn't quite tag it as the latent phase
of the new structure but he does
identify paradoxical reasoning as in a
category of its own entrance that
transitional between dialectical
reasoning it has this ability to hold
this paradox but resisting this tendency
to make the higher synthetic move
creates a completely different view and
so that is an important
phase two consider as we continue our
inquiry in the magellan course